Guide to the Columba Patrick Murray papers M2156
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Columba Patrick Murray papers
1898-1985
1918-1959
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Murray, Columba Patrick, 1898-1985
M2156
3.25 Linear Feet (3 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize box)
Biographical note
Columba Patrick Murray, Jr., was born in 1898 and died in Vienna, Austria, on September 23, 1985. He studied law at Georgetown University and eventually served in the ARA (American Relief Administration) in Russia from 1921-1923, as a major in the United States Army from 1942-1945, and in CARE (Cooperative for American Remittances to Europe) in post-war Poland and Austria from 1946-48.
Content Description
The materials consist of personal and professional correspondence, documents and photographs, mostly from 1918-1959, recording the activities of Major Columba Patrick Murray during a lifetime career associated with various U.S. consular, diplomatic, and military stations, most notably the ARA (American Relief Administration) in Russia, 1921-1923, and CARE (Cooperative for American Remittances to Europe) in post-war Poland and Austria. 231 manuscripts and typed letters and documents, various sizes, totaling 391 pages. Miscellaneous photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by Stanford University Libraries in 2014.
Reconstruction (1914-1939) -- Soviet Union; International relief -- Europe; Murray, Columba Patrick, 1898-1985; CARE Inc.; American Relief Administration
- American Relief Administration Bulletin, Series 2, No. 32, January 1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- The School of Military Government, Class Two, September 8th - December 29th, 1942: Major Murray on p. 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Kampf unter der Kriegsflagge eine Bildmappe vom Einsatz unserer Kriegsmarine: mit 18 Bildern nach Originalen von Marinemaler Adolf Bock und 16 BIldern nach Aufnahmen von Kriegsberichtern der Kriegsmarine: A portfolio of color and b&w reproductions of paintings of Adolf Bock, and of photographs taken by war correspondents (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Die Sächsische Schweiz, with inscription Februar 19, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bad Nauheim brochure and map (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Colomba Murray related ephemera including: birth certificate, 1898; selective service registration cards, 1918; registration for classes at Georgetown, 1918; newspaper mentioning audition with Pope, 1948; Engineer's certificate, 1922, 1898-03-05-1963-12-31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Newspaper clippings, most with biographical details on Colomba Murray (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Death certificate, notification of death to stepsisters and ephemera (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Information relating to death of Colomba Murray and material about his stay in Vienna (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence - Inter-family between Columba and his mother Maria, Margaret, Katie and Anne Murray (Ireland and New York), 1890-01-01-1926-03-25 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, Colomba Murray work-related, Washington, D.C., 1918-02-11-1919-06-11 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, including travel expenses of Colomba Murrary work-related, with Copenhagen, Moscow, Kiev, Odessa, London, Kazan, Riga, Peking, 1919-06-1924-03 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Travel orders issued to Columba Murray by the American Relief Administration in Russia, 1922/23 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Accounts and balances for Columba Murray while in service of ARA, Russia and Ukraine, 1921-12-1923-03-25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Reports of famine in Russia, 1921, including statistics of starving people by region and the services provided by ARA (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letters to Colomba Murray from females in Kiev, Odessa, Paris, 1923-1927 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence: to Columba Murray from William Vasily von Kleenam; between Columba Murray and Tong Shaoyi, Chinese politician and ephemera about him, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letters: Colomba Murray to his son, Colomba Jr. in China, 1923-10-1929-03 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  General
  Some letters very brittle
- Letters: Edward Leaky to Colomba Murray, 1933-1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence: to Columba Murray, various, about personal finances, requests for donations, 1923-1928 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence: Commission for Polish Relief, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Letters: Colomba Murray to sister, Mae Crewe, later Mae Sheridan, from Europe; correspondence with Sidney Larschan, 1944-1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters: Colomba Murray to sister, Mae Sheridan, from Europe, 1951-1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence: Colomba Murray and sister, Anne Flaherty, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Letters: Colomba Murray to Sidney Larschan, from Europe, 1947-03 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Commission at rank of Major on December 7, 1942, issued May 20, 1947 for service in WWII. Accompanying letter from Major General Witsell who issued the commission. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Pope John Paul II Indulgence document for Colomba Murray and family, 1982-07-22 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Ephemera relating to Colomba Murray: naturalization papers from 1897; reference letter from 1912; 3 small photographs of his wife and children, celtic graves in Ireland and wife's tomb in New York (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Ephemera and empty canceled envelopes (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Photographs of presentation to Colomba Murray of the decoration of A Knight of St. Gregory on behalf of the Holy Father by Cardinal Theodor Innitzer, Cardinal and Primate of Austria; other photographs of ceremonies, all with annotations. Press clippings and photographs relating to CARE (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Photographs from Waclaw Kuligowski in Poland of a woman in costumes (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Photographs of a room in New York City with a sign displaying Colomba P. Murray Jr. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Business cards of foreigners and ads found in newspapers; calling card of Cla Murray, Jr.; ephemera (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Photographs of Hilde, a romantic interest (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Photographs, some with annotations (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Photographs - Germany (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Photographs, mostly China (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Postcard photos, Chile (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Postcard family photos; three postcards with letters from Berlin (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Two photograph sets with annotations from Hilde (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Photographs of Colomba Murray as an adult; one photograph of a man; family postcard photos with letter from Colomba as a child to his father (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Four family photographs, tintypes (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Eire ein Irlandbuch von Joachim Gerstenberg, Hansestadt Hamburg, 1940, with an inscription on the inside dated 27 Januar 1942 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- The Sunday Star, Washington, D. C. Planogravure Section, November 24, 1918, Extremely brittle. (Flat-box 4, Folder 1)
- Morgen Express, den 7 April 1964, two copies; clipping from issue of Panarama-Queen 1964 (Flat-box 4, Folder 2)
- Life, December 23, 1940: photo of Commission for Polish Relief, p. 52 (Flat-box 4, Folder 3)